<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Sampling past periods</title>
    <para>Predictors can generate data values for periods that are in the past, present, or future.
        These values are based on data sampled from periods before the predicted period, and/or
        data from the predicted period. When you use data sampled from past periods (periods
        before the predicted period), several parameters determine the choice of which past
        periods to sample from:</para>
    <section xml:id="sequential_sample_count">
        <title>Sequential sample count</title>
        <para>A predictor's <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> gives the number of
            immediate prior periods to sample.
            For example, if a predictor's period type is <emphasis>Weekly</emphasis> and the
            <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> is 4, this means to sample four
            prior weeks immediately preceding the predicted value week. So the predicted
            value for week 9 would use samples from weeks 5, 6, 7, and 8:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_sequential.png" width="55%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>If a predictor's period type is <emphasis>Monthly</emphasis> and the
            <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> is 4, this means to sample four
            prior months immediately preceding the predicted value month. So the predicted
            value for May would use samples from weeks January, February, March, and April:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_sequential_month.png" width="55%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>The <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> can be greater than the number of
            periods in a year. For example, if you want to sample the 24 months immediately preceding
            the predicted value month, set the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> to 24:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_24_months.png" width="65%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sequential_skip_count">
        <title>Sequential skip count</title>
        <para>A predictor's <emphasis>Sequential skip count</emphasis> tells how many periods
            should be skipped immediately prior to the predicted value period,
            within the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis>.
            This could be used, for instance, in outbreak detection to skip one or more
            immediately prededing samples that might in fact contain values from the
            beginning of an outbreak that you are trying to detect.</para>
        <para>
            For example, if the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> is 4, but
            the <emphasis>Sequential skip count</emphasis> is 2, then the two samples
            immediately preceding the predicted period will be skipped, resulting in
            only two periods being sampled:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_skip.png" width="55%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="annual_sample_count">
        <title>Annual sample count</title>
        <para>A predictor's <emphasis>Annual sample count</emphasis> gives the number of
            prior years for which samples should be collected at the same time of year.
            This could be used, for instance, for disease surveillance in cases where the
            expected incidence of the disease varies during the year and can best be
            compared with the same relative period in previous years. For example, if
            the <emphasis>Annual sample count</emphasis> is 2 (and the <emphasis>Sequential
            sample count</emphasis> is zero), then samples would be collected
            from periods in the immediately preceding two years, at the same time of year.</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_annual.png" width="60%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sequential_annual_sample_count">
        <title>Sequential and annual sample counts together</title>
        <para>You can use the sequential and annual sample counts together to collect
            samples from a number of sequential periods over a number of past years.
            When you do this, samples will be collected in prior years during the
            period at the same time of year as the predicted value period, and also
            in previous years both before and after the same time of year, as determined
            by the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> number.</para>
        <para>For example, if the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> is 4
            and the <emphasis>Annual sample count</emphasis> is 2, samples will be
            collected from the 4 periods immediately preceding the predicted value period.
            In addition samples will be collected in the prior 2 years for the corresponding
            period, as well as 4 periods on either side:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_sequential_annual.png" width="75%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sequential_annual_skip_sample_count">
        <title>Sequential, annual, and skip sample counts together</title>
        <para>You can use the <emphasis>Sequential skip count</emphasis> together
            with the sequential and annual sample counts. When you do this, the
            <emphasis>Sequential skip count</emphasis> tells how many periods to
            skip in the same year as the predicted value period. For
            example, if the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis> is 4
            and the <emphasis>Sequential skip count</emphasis> is 2, then the
            two preiods immediatly preceding the predicted value period period
            will be skipped, but the two periods before that will be sampled:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_skip_2_weeks.png" width="75%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>If the <emphasis>Sequential skip count</emphasis> is
            equal to or greater than the <emphasis>Sequential sample count</emphasis>,
            then no samples will be collected for the year containing the
            predicted value period; only periods from past years will be sampled:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_skip_current_year.png" width="75%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sample_skip_test">
        <title>Sample skip test</title>
        <para>You can use the <emphasis>Sample skip test</emphasis> to skip
            samples from certain periods that would otherwise be included, based on
            the results of testing an expression within those periods.
            This could be used, for instance, in disease outbreak detection, where
            the sample skip test could identify previous disease outbreaks, to exclude
            those samples from the prediction of a non-outbreak baseline expected value.</para>
        <para>The <emphasis>Sample skip test</emphasis> is an expression that should
            return a value of true or false, to indicate whether or not the period should
            be skipped. It can be an expression that tests any values in the preiovus
            period. For example, it could test for a data value that was explicitly
            entered to indicate that a previous period should be skipped. Or it could
            compare a previously predicted value for a period with the actual value
            recorded for that period, to determine if that period should be skipped.</para>
        <para>Any periods for which the <emphasis>Sample skip test</emphasis>
            is <emphasis>true</emphasis> will not be sampled. For example:</para>
        <para></para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/predictor_sample_skip_test.png" width="75%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para></para>
    </section>
</section>
