<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="about_program_rules">
    <title>About program rules</title>
    <para>Program rules allows you to create and control dynamic behavior of the user interface in
        the <emphasis role="bold">Tracker Capture</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Event
            Capture</emphasis> apps. During data entry, the program rules expressions are evaluated
        each time the user interface is displayed, and each time a data element is changed. Most
        types of actions will take effect immediately when the user enters values in the <emphasis
            role="bold">Tracker Capture</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Event
            Capture</emphasis> apps.</para>
    <table frame="all">
        <title>Program rule components</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule component</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Description</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule action</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Each program rule contains one or multiple actions. These are the
                            behaviors that are triggered in the user interface when the expression
                            is true. Actions will be applied at once if the expression is true, and
                            will be reverted if the expression is no longer true. There are several
                            types of actions and you can have several actions in one program
                            rule.</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule expression</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Each program rule has a single expression that determines whether the
                            program rule actions should be triggered, if the expression evaluates to
                            true. If the expression is true the program rule is in effect and the
                            actions will be executed. If the expression is false, the program rule
                            is no longer in effect and the actions will no longer be applied. </para>
                        <para>You create the expression with standard mathematical operators, custom
                            functions, user-defined static values and program rule variables. The
                            program rule variables represent attribute and data element values which
                            will be evaluated as part of the expression.</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule variable</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule variables lets you include data values and attribute
                            values in program rule expressions. Typically, you'll have to create one
                            or several program rule variables before creating a program rule. This
                            is because program rules expressions usually contain at least one data
                            element or attribute value to be meaningful.</para>
                        <para>The program rule variables are shared between all rules in your
                            program. When you create multiple program rules for the same program,
                            these rules will share the same library of program rule
                            variables.</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance</emphasis> app, you manage the following program
        rule objects:</para>
    <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Object type</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Available functions</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Create, edit, clone, delete, show details and translate</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Program rule variable</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Create, edit, clone, share, delete, show details and translate</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
</section>
