<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
 <chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Unicef lmis use case</title>
  <para/>
  <section>
    <title>Integration concepts</title>
    <para>DHIS2 is an open platform and its implementers are active contributors to interoperability
      initiatives, such as openHIE. The DHIS2 application database is designed with flexibility in
      mind. Data structures such as data elements, organisation units, forms and user roles can be
      defined completely freely through the application user interface. This makes it possible for
      the system to be adapted to a multitude of local contexts and use-cases. DHIS2 supports many
      requirements for routine data capture and analysis emerging in country implementations. It
      also makes it possible for DHIS2 to serve as a basic management system in domains such as
        <emphasis role="underline">logistics, laboratory management and finance</emphasis>.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Integration</title>
      <para>Based on its platform approach, DHIS2 is able to receive and host data from different
        data sources and share it to other systems and reporting mechanisms. An important
        distinction of integration concepts is the difference between data integration and systems
        interoperability:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>When talking about <emphasis role="bold">integration</emphasis>, we think about the
            process of making different information systems appear as one, making data available to
            all relevant users as well as the harmonization of definitions and dimensions so that it
            is possible to combine the data in useful ways.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A related concept is <emphasis role="bold">interoperability</emphasis>, which is one
            strategy to achieve integration. We consider DHIS2 interoperable with other software
            applications because of its capability to exchange data. For example, DHIS2 and OpenMRS
            are interoperable, because they allow to share data definitions and data with each
            other. Interoperability depends on standards for data formats, interfaces and codes and
            terminologies. These would ideally be internationally balloted standards, but in
            practice may also consist of de facto standards</para>
          <para>and other more local agreements within a particular context. A de facto standard is
            something which has wide acceptance and usage but not necessarily formally balloted in a
            standards development organisation</para>
          <para/>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
