<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xml:id="user_story_kurdistan">
    <title>DHIS2 in the Autonomous Region of Kurdistan, Iraq</title>
    <para><emphasis>For the citizens of war-torn Iraq, as well as for the thousands of refugees
            stranded in camps across the Autonomous Region of Iraqi Kurdistan, getting access to
            regular health care is not a straightforward procedure.</emphasis></para>
    <section><para><emphasis role="bold">In June 2015, a DHIS2 Health Information System</emphasis> was set up to
            assist the Kurdish health authorities in collecting population data and improving the
            access and quality of public health care.<screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ui.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="70%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para></section>
    <section>
        <para>A KRG-DHIS2 pilot project led by the University of Tor Vergata, Rome, and realized by
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://ipro.orgipro-it.eu/">I-PRO</link> and <link
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.euresist.org/"
                >EuResist Network</link> was deployed across a set of pilot health centers and
            hospitals in the Kurdish directorates of Erbil, Duhok and Slemani.<screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_map.png" format="PNG"
                            align="left" width="70%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>Image: Created with DHIS2 GIS app, © UiO, 2016
            </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">With 60 registered users spread across 30 health centers</emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold">700 Kurdish medical professionals</emphasis> can now follow a staggering <emphasis role="bold">180,000 health events</emphasis>! Indeed, just 18 months into the pilot project, there are
            now 7 primary/family health centers, 9 hospitals, and 14 general health centers. There are currently 10
            health centers in rural areas such as small towns or villages, and there are 20 health centers in major
            towns. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">110,000 cases</emphasis> have been imported via periodic uploads
            from existing and running databases, and 70,000 cases have been recorded by DHIS2 users.
            This great progress is enabling health professionals to gather statistics for disease
            diagnoses, hospital discharges, registrations of births, deaths and
            immunizations.
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_screen1.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="90%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The project is also using the WHO International Classification
            of Diseases</emphasis> (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/icd/en/">WHO ICD-10</link>), which is the
            standard diagnostic tool for epidemiology, health management and research purposes. This
            classification defines the universe of diseases, disorders, injuries and other related
            health conditions, listed in a comprehensive, hierarchical way. The data can be: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Easily stored, retrieved and analyzed for evidenced-based decision-making;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Used for sharing and comparing health information between hospitals,
                        regions, settings and countries;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Used to compare data in the same location across different periods.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Key implementation challenges</title>
        <para>With such a small time-frame to implement and deploy a DHIS2 epidemiological
            surveillance pilot project across the entire Kurdish region of Iraq, there are still
            many challenges ahead for the teams involved.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Racing against the clock. </emphasis>The first challenge lies in
            building a solution that works in a short time and satisfies the basic needs of the
            regional health system in collecting data. So far, a subset of the regional health
            centers, approximately 30 establishments, made up of rural and urban centers, family
            health centers, hospitals, hospital colleges, and general health centers have been
            involved in testing the system.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Pulling in data from other systems. </emphasis>Another challenge
            lies in making it possible to import existing data from hospitals into DHIS2 while also
            making it achievable to enter data from mobile devices. Additional challenges lie in
            preparing reports equal to those requested by the health authorities, and building a
            DHIS2 system for people who don’t necessarily have a background in health.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Testing using a small, live version of DHIS2. </emphasis>The
            testing phase covered two areas: creating data sets with aggregate data entry and making
            programs with disaggregate event data capture. After analyzing the data reports produced
            by the tests, the project managers decided to use programs without registration using
            the Event Capture app.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Capturing data with the Event Capture app. </emphasis> In this
            region of Iraq, people do not have identification numbers. It's therefore almost
            impossible to follow patients' visits to different health centers. Bearing this in mind,
            the team built a system to record basic health events such as births, deaths,
            immunizations, disease diagnoses and hospital discharges using the Event Capture
            app.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Why the Event Capture app? </emphasis>On the one hand, this app
            allows you to import existing data from hospital databases, while adhering to the same
            data structure. On the other hand, physicians or health technicians can enter data in
            real-time during a visit, without having to complete further data aggregation tasks.
            These two key areas combined were very helpful to our teams.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hosting.</emphasis> Without the means to implement a dedicated
            server, we chose to use an outsourced hosting solution through a recommended company
            called <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="https://baosystems.com/">BAO Systems</link>. With this solution we will
            be able to scale up our DHIS2 instance in the future.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translating the UI into Kurdish-Sorani. </emphasis> With the
            help of the DHIS2 community, DHIS2 developers and a translation team, the DHIS2 user
            interface is now available in Kurdish-Sorani, a language spoken by 6 million people in
            Iraq.</para>
        <para>The task of translating the UI was at times challenging. Indeed, some parts of the
            data model could not be directly translated into Kurdish-Sorani as there wasn’t always
            an equivalent term in the target language. For example, the terms “description of report
            date” remained in three languages in the UI: English, Arabic and Kurdish-Sorani as
            follows: Date of birth / تاريخ الولادة / بةرواري لة دايك بوون 
            </para>
        <para>Likewise, another highly technical problem was the lack of Kurdish-Sorani in the base method, which relies on locales present in the underlying Java library. Plainly speaking, the Kurdish-Sorani
            language was not supported by DHIS2 dependencies. </para>
            <para>The screen captures here show how the
            user interface looks in both English and Kurdish-Sorani: <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_screen2.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="90%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_screen3.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="90%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>            
    </section>
    <section><title>What's ahead?</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Creating national health numbers for all citizens of the Autonomous Region of Iraqi Kurdistan. </emphasis>  The first focus for the upcoming years is to introduce a national health identity (HNID) for each citizen accessing health services provided by the hospitals and health centers monitored by and coordinated with the MOH of the KRG. Once this is in place, the HNID will be integrated into the Kurdish DHIS2 platform. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Expanding the system for a complete coverage of the Autonomous
                Region of Kurdistan.</emphasis> The second major goal set for 2021 is to involve at
            least 300 health centers in the KRG-DHIS2 platform, in order to reach a complete
            coverage of the territory.</para>
        <para>The final overall aim is to set up a <emphasis role="bold">high-quality
                epidemiological health surveillance system </emphasis> in the Autonomous Region of
            Kurdistan. While achieving this goal, the teams hope to extend their DHIS2 expertise to
            other areas besides health, such as programs of demographic or environmental interest. </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>In the news</title>
        <para>If you'd like to view a presentation of the DHIS2-KRG project to the Kurdish
            government and Italian Ministry of foreign Affairs, here’s a recent <link
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-jIOUJkVGJw&amp;feature=em-uploademail"
                >video</link>: <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_video.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="80%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-jIOUJkVGJw&amp;feature=em-uploademail"
                >Kurdistan Region, DHIS2 Health Monitoring System</link>Video source: Kurdistan
            Region, DHIS2 Health Monitoring System, © IPRO Research, Oct. 2016. </para></section>
    <section><title>Handy resources</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Follow the progress of the KRG-DHIS2 project on I-PRO's <link
                            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://www.informapro.it/krg-dhis.html">web
                        page</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>KRG-DHIS2 end-user documentation: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>KRG – DHIS Health Monitoring System <link
                                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                        xlink:href="https://krg-dhis.ipro-it.eu/api/documents/b8Uobi3Hqri/data"
                                        >USER MANUAL - ver. 2016 February</link></para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>KRG – DHIS2 Health Monitoring System - <link
                                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                        xlink:href="https://krg-dhis.ipro-it.eu/api/documents/tLCQli1uX2K/data"
                                        >How to do… Additional Documentation</link></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>KRG-DHIS2 <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwRF39H2QHFbx2WzDfxFPSjxwpmcN6ERZ"
                            >playlist on YouTube</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para></section>
    <section><title>Contact us!</title>
        <para>We are very keen to give feedback about the progress we are making with our KRG-DHIS2
            project. If you’d like to ask us questions about our work you can reach out to us as follows:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="mailto:leonardo.emberti.gialloreti@uniroma2.it">Mr.
                                Leonardo Emberti Gialloreti</link></emphasis>:  Project leader and
                        medical supervisor University of Tor Vergata, Rome, Italy.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para><screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_opening_training_center.png"
                        format="PNG" align="left" width="80%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>Opening a DHIS2 training center in KRG, (c) IPRO 2016.</para></section>
</chapter>
