<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xml:id="user_story_kurdistan">
    <title>DHIS2 in the Autonomous Region of Kurdistan</title>
    <para><emphasis>For the thousands of refugees stranded in camps across the war-torn Autonomous
            Region of Iraqi Kurdistan, getting access to regular health care hasn’t always been
            straightforward.</emphasis></para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Set up in 2015 by the University of Rome Tor Vergata (Italy) with the
                    Ministry of Health of Kurdistan Regional Government (KRG).</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Funded by the Cooperation and Development Agency of the Ministry of
                    Foreign Affairs of Italy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Deployed by <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://ipro.orgipro-it.eu/">I-PRO</link>.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Compliant with <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/icd/en/">WHO ICD-10</link>
                    standards. </emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>700 doctors trained in ICD-10.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>130,000 health events registered so far in the system.
                </emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Bilingual English and Kurdish-Sorani DHIS2 interface. </emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section><para><emphasis role="bold">In June 2015, a DHIS2 Health Information System</emphasis> was set up to
            assist the Kurdish health authorities in collecting population data and improving the
            access and quality of public health care.</para></section>
    <section>
        <para>A KRG-DHIS2 pilot project led by the University of Tor Vergata, Rome, and realized by
            IPRO and Euresist was deployed across a set of pilot health centers and hospitals in the
            Kurdish directorates of Erbil, Duhok and Slemani.<screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_terrain.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="60%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para><para><emphasis role="bold">With 60 registered users spread across 30 health centers</emphasis>,
            Kurdish medical professionals can now follow a staggering <emphasis role="bold">150,000
                health events</emphasis>! Indeed, just 16 months into the pilot project, there are
            now 7 primary/family health centers, 9 hospitals, and 14 general health centers, 10
            health centers in rural areas or small towns/villages, and 20 health centers in major
            towns. </para>
        <para>100,000 cases have been imported via periodic uploads from existing and running
            databases, and 50,000 cases have been recorded by DHIS2 users. This great progress is
            enabling health professionals to gather statistics for disease diagnoses, hospital
            discharges, registrations of births, deaths and immunizations.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The project is also using the WHO’s International Classification
                of Diseases</emphasis> (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/icd/en/">ICD-10</link>), which is the
            standard diagnostic tool for epidemiology, health management and clinical purposes. So
            far, over 700 doctors and nurses have received specialized ICD-10 training and
            epidemiological surveillance training.</para>
        <para>If you'd like a summary, view a video of the project here: <link
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-jIOUJkVGJw&amp;feature=em-uploademail"
                >Kurdistan Region, DHIS2 Health Monitoring System - October 2016</link>.</para></section>
    <section><title>DHIS2 - the best choice available</title><para>After conducting a thorough benchmarking of six software platforms that can be found with a
            tight budget, DHIS2 was selected as the most promising, all-encompassing software. Those
            involved in the assessment got affirmative answers to all of these key points regarding DHIS2:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This software enables you to define the composition of the local health
                        management system.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It enables you to define the hierarchy between health structures.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It records aggregated data and case by case data.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It uses smart phones and SMS as data entry points.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It works offline and is web-based.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It's intended for health institutions and governments.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It has a good track record: already adopted and assessed in several
                        countries.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>It has a strong user network for supporting development and
                        implementation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>There are good training programs available for users.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para></section>
    <section>
        <title>Key implementation challenges</title>
        <para>With a small time frame to get a DHIS2 epidemiological surveillance pilot project
            implemented and deployed in the whole Kurdish region of Iraq, many challenges lay ahead
            for the teams involved.</para>
        <para>The first challenge lay in building a solution that would work in a short time. One
            that would satisfy at the very least the basic needs of the regional health system in
            collecting data.</para>
        <para>A subset of the regional health centers came on board; rural and urban centers, family
            health centers, hospitals, hospital colleges and general health centers were involved in
            the pilot project. These centers, roughly around 30 establishments, tested the system,
            its feasibility and functions.</para>
        <para/>
    </section>
</chapter>

