<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xml:id="user_story_kurdistan">
    <title>DHIS2 in the Autonomous Region of Kurdistan</title>
    <para><emphasis>For the thousands of refugees stranded in camps across the war-torn Autonomous
            Region of Iraqi Kurdistan, getting access to regular health care hasn’t always been
            straightforward.</emphasis><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_map.png"
                    format="PNG" align="left" width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>
    <section><para><emphasis role="bold">In June 2015, a DHIS2 Health Information System</emphasis> was set up to
            assist the Kurdish health authorities in collecting population data and improving the
            access and quality of public health care.</para></section>
    <section>
        <para>A KRG-DHIS2 pilot project led by the University of Tor Vergata, Rome, and realized by
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://ipro.orgipro-it.eu/">I-PRO</link> and Euresist was deployed across a set of pilot health centers and hospitals in the
            Kurdish directorates of Erbil, Duhok and Slemani.<screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ui.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="70%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para><para><emphasis role="bold">With 60 registered users spread across 30 health centers</emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold">700 Kurdish medical professionals</emphasis> can now follow a staggering <emphasis role="bold">150,000
                health events</emphasis>! Indeed, just 16 months into the pilot project, there are
            now 7 primary/family health centers, 9 hospitals, and 14 general health centers, 10
            health centers in rural areas or small towns/villages, and 20 health centers in major
            towns. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">100,000 cases</emphasis> have been imported via periodic uploads
            from existing and running databases, and 50,000 cases have been recorded by DHIS2 users.
            This great progress is enabling health professionals to gather statistics for disease
            diagnoses, hospital discharges, registrations of births, deaths and
            immunizations.
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_screen.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="90%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The project is also using the WHO’s International Classification
            of Diseases</emphasis> (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/icd/en/">WHO ICD-10</link>), which is the
            standard diagnostic tool for epidemiology, health management and research purposes. This
            classification defines the universe of diseases, disorders, injuries and other related
            health conditions, listed in a comprehensive, hierarchical way. The data can be: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Easily stored, retrieved and analysed for evidenced-based decision-making;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Used for sharing and comparing health information between hospitals,
                        regions, settings and countries;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Making data comparisons in the same location across different time
                        periods</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist> If you'd like a summary of this implementation of DHIS2, you can view a
            video of the project here: <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-jIOUJkVGJw&amp;feature=em-uploademail"
                >Kurdistan Region, DHIS2 Health Monitoring System - October 2016</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Key implementation challenges</title>
        <para>With a small time frame to get a DHIS2 epidemiological surveillance pilot project
            implemented and deployed in the whole Kurdish region of Iraq, many challenges lay ahead
            for the teams involved.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Racing against the clock. </emphasis>The first challenge lay in
            building a solution that would work in a short time; one that would satisfy the basic
            needs of the regional health system in collecting data. A subset of the regional health
            centers, approximately 30 establishments, made up of rural and urban centers, family
            health centers, hospitals, hospital colleges and general health centers were involved in
            testing the system.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Pulling in data from other systems. </emphasis>Another challenge
            lay in importing existing data already used in hospitals in to DHIS2; making it possible
            to enter data from mobile devices; preparing reports equal to those requested from the
            health centers by the health directorates; and building a DHIS2 system to be used by
            people without a background in health. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Testing using a small, live version of DHIS2.</emphasis> The
            testing phase was centered around two areas: data sets with aggregate data entry, and
            programs with disaggregate event data capture. After analyzing the data reports produced
            by the tests, the project managers decided to use programs without registration using
            the Event Capture app.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Capturing data with the Event Capture app.</emphasis> In this
            region of Iraq, people do not have identification numbers. It's therefore almost
            impossible to follow patients' visits to different health centers. Bearing this in mind,
            we decided to build a system to record basic health events such as births, deaths,
            immunizations, disease diagnoses and hospital discharges using the Event Capture app.
            Using this app, you can import existing data from hospital databases while adhering to
            the same data structure, which is extremely helpful. Physicians or other health
            technicians are able to enter data in real-time while a visitation is taking place,
            without having to complete further data aggregation operations. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hosting.</emphasis> Without the means to implement a dedicated
            server, we chose to use an outsourced hosting solution through a recommended company
            called <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="https://baosystems.com/">BAO Systems</link>. With this solution we will
            be able to scale up our DHIS2 instance in the future.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translating the UI into Kurdish-Sorani.</emphasis> With the help
            of the DHIS2 community and its developers and translation team, we were able to
            translate the DHIS2 user interface into Kurdish-Sorani, a language which is spoken by 6
            million people in Iraq.</para>
        <para>This is how the user interface looks in English and Kurdish-Sorani: <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_screen2.png"
                        format="PNG" align="left" width="90%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_ipro_screen3.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="90%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></para>            
    </section>
    <section><title>What's ahead?</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Creating national health numbers for all citizens</emphasis>  Our
            main focus for the upcoming years is to introduce a national health identity (HNID) for
            each citizen accessing health services. Once this is in place, we plan to integrate the
            HNID into the Kurdish DHIS2 platform. Furthermore, we plan to involve at least 300
            health centers in our KRG-DHIS2 platform. Finally, our aim is to grow and to extend
            DHIS2 to other areas besides health.</para>
        <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/kurdistan_opening_training_center.png"
                            format="PNG" align="left" width="80%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
        </screenshot><para>Opening a DHIS2 training center in KRG, (c) IPRO 2016.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
