<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="about_maps">
    <title>About the Maps app</title>
    <para>The Maps App is introduced in release 2.29 and serves as a replacement of the GIS App
        offering a more intuitive and user-friendly interface.</para>
    <para>With the Maps app you can overlay multiple layers and choose among different base maps.
        You can create thematic maps of areas and points, view facilities based on classifications,
        and visualize catchment areas for each facility. You can add labels to areas and points, and
        search and filter using various criteria. You can move points and set locations on the fly.
        Maps can be saved as favorites and shared with other users and groups.</para>
    <para>
        <note>
            <para>To use predefined legends in the <emphasis role="bold">Maps</emphasis> app, you
                need to create them first in the <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance</emphasis>
                app.</para>
        </note>
    </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
            <title>Here's an overview of the Maps app workspace</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="resources/images/maps/maps_main.png" align="center"
                        width="100%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">layer panel</emphasis> on the left side of the workspace
                shows an overview of the layers for the current map:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>As layers are added, using the (+) Add layer button, they are arranged and
                        managed in this panel.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">basemap</emphasis> is always shown in the panel.
                        The default basemap is OSM Light and is selected by default. OpenStreetMap
                        Detailed,
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160412T152838+0200" comment="Use of trademarks in documentaiton and interface must be reviewed.
https://www.google.com/permissions/trademark/trademark-list.html
" id="pjt_gvs_xcb" mid="1"?><?oxy_comment_start author="philld" timestamp="20180220T082207+0100" comment="The trademarks here are in line with Googles requirements on trademark use." parentID="pjt_gvs_xcb"?>Google
                        Streets and Google Hybrid<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="1"?> are
                        also available. You can use these maps as background maps and layers. Switch
                        between them by selecting the desired image.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The small arrow button to the right of the layer panel, at the top, allows
                        the panel to be hidden or shown. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para></para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> button near the top left allows you
                to save and open maps:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>New             </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will clear any existing map layers to create a new thematic map.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Open</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will display a <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> dialog to
                            select an existing thematic map. Favorites can also be renamed, shared
                            and deleted through the Favorites dialog. <emphasis>The title of the
                                current favorite is displayed in the header bar above the Favorites
                                button.</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Save</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will save any changes to the current favorite.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Save as</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will save the current thematic map as a new favorite.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Write interpretation</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will open a dialog where an interpretation for the current favorite
                            can be written.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Get link</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will provide a direct link and API link to the current
                            favorite.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-
                </emphasis>buttons on the map allow you to zoom in and out of the map respectively.
                The mouse scroll wheel can also be used for altering the zoom.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Zoom to content</emphasis> (bounded magnifying glass symbol)
                automatically adjusts the zoom level and map center position to put the data on your
                map in focus.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis> (magnifying glass symbol) allows searching
                for and jumping to a location on the map.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">ruler</emphasis> button allows you to find the distance
                between two locations on the map.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To view information for an event, simply click the event.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Right-click on the map to display the longitude and latitude of that
                location.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The home icon on the top right of the workspace will take you back to the DHIS2
                dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The About button will display system version information.</para>

        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para/>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Basemaps</emphasis></para>
            <para>Basemap layers are represented by layer <emphasis>cards</emphasis> in the layer
                panel such as:</para>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/maps/maps_basemap_card.png"
                            format="png" align="left" width="40%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Along the top of the basemap card from left to right are:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The title of the selected basemap</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An eye symbol for toggling the visibility of the layer</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An arrow symbol to collapse and expand the basemap card</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>In the middle of the basemap card is the list of available basemaps. The current basemap is highlighted.</para>
            <para>Along the bottom of the basemap card is:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A slider for modifying the layer transparency</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
    
</section>
