<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="enter_data_offline">
  <title>Enter data offline</title>
  <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Data Entry</emphasis> app works even if you don't have a stable
    Internet connectivity during data entry. In order to utilize this functionality, you must login
    to the server while Internet connectivity is present, but if during data entry, the Internet
    link between your computer and the server becomes unstable, data can still be entered into the
    data entry form, saved to your local computer, and then pushed to the server once the Internet
    connectivity has been restored. Data can be entered and stored locally while being off-line and
    uploaded to the central server when on-line. This means that the on-line deployment strategy
    will be more viable in areas with unstable Internet connectivity. The total bandwidth usage is
    greatly reduced since forms no longer are retrieved from the server for each rendering.</para>
  <section xml:id="data_entry_with_dhis2">
    <section>
      <para>When the server is able to be reached through the Internet connection, a message is
        displayed at the top of the data entry screen below. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center"
              fileref="resources/images/data_entry/data_entry_online1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>If the Internet connection should disconnect for some reason during the data entry
        process, this will be detected by the application, and you will be informed that your data
        will be stored locally. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center"
              fileref="resources/images/data_entry/data_entry_offline1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Data entry can proceed as normal. Once you have entered all of the necessary data, and
        the application detects that the server is back on-line, you will be informed that you have
        data which needs to be synchronized with the server. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center"
              fileref="resources/images/data_entry/data_entry_offline_upload.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Once the data has successfully synchronized with the server, you will receive a
        confirmation message that the data has been successfully uploaded to the server. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center"
              fileref="resources/images/data_entry/data_entry_offline_upload_success1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
